[{"question": "Question", "options": ["Option A", "Option B", "Option C", "Option D"], "correctoption": "Correct Option"}, {"question": "An object takes $\\mathbf{n}$ times as much time as to slide down a $45^{\\circ}$ rough inclined plane as it takes to slide down perfectly smooth inclined planned of the same inclination. The coefficient of kinetic friction between the object and the rough incline is given by\\\\", "options": ["$\\left(1-\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}}\\right)$\\\\", "$\\left(\\frac{1}{1-\\mathrm{n}^{2}}\\right)$\\\\", "$\\sqrt{1-\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}}}$\\\\", "$\\sqrt{1+\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}}}$"], "correctoption": "a"}, {"question": "A block of mass $m$ is in contact with the cart $C$ as shown in the figure.\n\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_03_13_359c50466f35fd3720b7g-080(2)}\n\\end{center}\n\nThe coefficient of static friction between the block and the cart is $\\mu$. The acceleration $\\alpha$ of the cart that will prevent the block from falling satisfies\\\\", "options": ["$\\alpha>\\frac{\\mathrm{mg}}{\\mu}$\\\\", "$\\alpha>\\frac{\\mathrm{g}}{\\mu \\mathrm{m}}$\\\\", "$\\alpha \\geq \\frac{\\mathrm{g}}{\\mu}$\\\\", "$\\alpha<\\frac{g}{\\mu}$"], "correctoption": "c"}, {"question": "A boy throws a cricket ball from the boundary to the wicket keeper. If the frictional force due to air $\\left(f_{\\mathrm{a}}\\right.$ ) cannot be ignored, the forces acting on the ball at the position $X$ are represented by\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_03_13_359c50466f35fd3720b7g-087(2)}\n\\end{center}", "options": ["\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{nlm349a}\n\\end{center}", "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{nlm349b}\n\\end{center}", "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{nlm349c}\n\\end{center}", "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{nlm349d}\n\\end{center}"], "correctoption": "c"}, {"question": "Match List I with List II\n\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{emw3q}\n\\end{center}\n\n\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :\\\\", "options": ["A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4\\\\", "A-4, B-1, C-2, D-3\\\\", "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2\\\\", "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1"], "correctoption": "b"}, {"question": "In a plane EM wave the electric field oscillates sinusoidally at a frequency of $30 \\mathrm{MHz}$ and amplitude $150 \\mathrm{~V} / \\mathrm{m}$. Identify the correct expression of $\\vec{B}$ assuming the wave is propagating along $\\mathrm{x}$-axis and is oscillating along $\\mathbf{y}$-axis.", "options": ["$5 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\frac{\\mathrm{x}}{3}-6 \\times 10^{+7} \\mathrm{t}\\right] \\hat{z} \\mathrm{~T}$", "$5 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\pi\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{x}}{5}-6 \\times 10^{+7} \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{z}} \\mathrm{T}$", "$5 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\pi\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{x}}{10}-3 \\times 10^{+7} \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{z} ~ T}$", "$5 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\pi\\left(\\frac{2 \\mathrm{x}}{5}-6 \\times 10^{+8} \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{z}} \\mathrm{T}$"], "correctoption": "b"}, {"question": "Maxwell's equations regarding electromagnetic wave describe the fundamental laws of", "options": ["Electricity only", "Inagnetism only", "Mechanics only", "Both of electricity and magnetism"], "correctoption": "d"}, {"question": "A box of mass $2 \\mathrm{~kg}$ is placed on a inclined plane that makes $30^{\\circ}$ with the horizontal. The coefficient of friction between the box and inclined plane is 0.2 . A force $F$ is applied on the box perpendicular to the incline to prevent the box from sliding down. The minimum value of $F$ is(acceleration due to gravity $(\\mathrm{g})=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$ )\n\n\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth, center]{2024_03_13_359c50466f35fd3720b7g-084(1)}\\\\", "options": ["$28.6 \\mathrm{~N}$\\\\", "$22.8 \\mathrm{~N}$\\\\", "$32.7 \\mathrm{~N}$\\\\", "$44.6 \\mathrm{~N}$"], "correctoption": "c"}, {"question": "The centre of mass of an extended body on the surface of the earth and its centre of gravity", "options": ["Can never be at the same point", "Centre of mass coincides with the centre of gravity of a body if the size of the body is negligible as compared to the size (or radius) of the earth", "Are always at the same point for any size of the body", "Are always at the same point only for spherical bodies"], "correctoption": "b"}, {"question": "Consider a system of two particles having masses ' $m_{1}$ ' and ' $m_{2}$ '. If the particle of mass $m_{1}$ is pushed towards the centre of mass of the particles through a distance ' $d$ ', by what distance particle of mass $\\mathrm{m}_{2}$ move so as to keep the centre of mass of particles at the original position?", "options": ["$\\frac{\\mathrm{m}_{2}}{\\mathrm{~m}_{1}} \\times \\mathrm{d}$", "$\\frac{\\mathrm{m}_{1}}{\\left(\\mathrm{~m}_{1} \\times \\mathrm{m}_{2}\\right)} \\times \\mathrm{d}$", "$\\frac{\\mathrm{m}_{1}}{\\mathrm{~m}_{2}} \\times \\mathrm{d}$", "d"], "correctoption": "c"}, {"question": "Match the items given in Column I with those in Column II and select the correct option given below:\n\n$\n\\begin{array}{|l|l|l|}\n\\hline \\text { (A) } \\text { Herbarium } & \\begin{array}{l}\n\\text { (i) It is a place having a collection } \\\\\n\\text { of preserved plants and animals }\n\\end{array} \\\\ \n\\hline \\text { (B) } \\text { Key } & \\begin{array}{l}\n\\text { ( ii) A list that enumerates } \\\\\n\\text { methodically all the species } \\\\\n\\text { found in an area with brief } \\\\\n\\text { description aiding } \\\\\n\\text { identification }\n\\end{array} \\\\ \n\\hline \\text { (C) }\\text { Museum } & \\begin{array}{l}\n\\text {(iii) Is a place where dried and } \\\\\n\\text { pressed plant specimens } \\\\\n\\text { mounted on sheets are kept }\n\\end{array} \\\\\n\\hline \\text { (D) }\\text { Catalogue } &\\begin{array}{l}\n\\text { (iv) A booklet containing a list of } \\\\\n\\text { characters and their alternates } \\\\\n\\text { which are helpful in } \\\\\n\\text { identification of various taxa. }\n\\end{array} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\end{array}\n$", "options": ["A(i) , B(iv) , C(iii) , D(ii)", "A(iii) , B(ii) ,C(i) , D(iv)", "A(iii) , B(iv) , C(i) , D(ii)", "A(ii) , B(iv) , C(iii) , (i)"], "correctoption": "c"}]